Let's apply our knowledge of HTML to a real page.
لنطبق جميع ما تعلمناه عن لغة HTML على صفحة حقيقية.
Here's a Wikipedia article.
إليكم مقال على موقع Wikipedia.
I'll use my browser to see its source.
سأستخدم متصفحي لمعرفة مصدره.
I'm using Google Chrome but every browser has a view source button.
أنا أستخدم Google Chrome وكل متصفح به زر عرض المصدر.
It just might not be in the same place as it is in Chrome.
قد لا يكون في المكان نفسه كما هو في Chrome.
This HTML isn't as tidy as the example we looked at before.
صفحة HTML هذه ليست مرتبة مثل المثال الذي أطلعنا عليه من قبل.
Unlike Python, HTML doesn't require indentation or organization.
على عكس Python، إن HTML لا تتطلب مسافات بادئة أو ترتيبات.
If you scroll through it though we can see some familiar tags.
إذا مررتم خلالها، يمكننا أن نرى بعض العلامات المألوفة.
Here's a paragraph, some divs and some a herf tags.
توجد هنا فقرة وبعض عناصر div وبعض علامات herf.
Let's switch back to the rendered version of the page.
لنرجع إلى الإصدار المعروض من الصفحة.
Okay, the first link in the page is this link to the Monty Python article.
حسنًا، الرابط الأول في الصفحة هو هذا الرابط الذي ينقل إلى مقالة Monty Python.
Let's try to find that in the source code.
لنجرب العثور عليه في الكود المصدر.
Here it is. It looks like the article's text begins right here.
ها هو. يبدو أن نص المقالة يبدأ من هنا.
This link is inside a paragraph tag,
يوجد هذا الرابط بين علامة الفقرة،
but I can't really tell if the paragraph tag is inside of any other tags.
لكن لا يمكنني معرفة ما إذا كانت علامة الفقرة موجودة داخل أي علامات أخرى.
There's just too much unformatted HTML for me to read.
هناك الكثير من لغات HTML غير المنسقة كي أقرأها.
Fortunately, browsers have tools to make this manageable.
لحسن الحظ، تحتوي المتصفحات على أدوات للتحكم في ذلك.
I want to close this source code tab and open the developer tools.
أود إغلاق علامة كود المصدر هذه وفتح أدوات المطور.
These developer tools aren't unique to Chrome.
لا تختلف أدوات المطور هذه عن Chrome.
Every browser has something similar.
يحتوي كل متصفح على شيء مماثل.
Okay, now we have an organized view of the HTML.
حسنا، لدينا الآن عرض منظم لصفحة HTML.
I can right click the first link and choose Inspect.
يمكنني أن أنقر بزر الماوس الأيمن فوق الرابط الأول واختيار فحص.
Then the tree of elements in the Tools panel
بعد ذلك يتم توسيع شجرة العناصر في لوحة الأدوات
expands to show the hierarchy of tags that lead to the link.
لإظهار التسلسل الهرمي للعلامات التي تؤدي إلى الرابط.
It looks like the first link is this a herf tag which is inside of this paragraph tag,
يبدو أن الرابط الأول هو علامة herf الموجودة بداخل علامة الفقرة،
which is inside of this div.
والتي توجد بداخل عنصر div هذا.
The div's ID is mw-content-text.
معرف عنصر div هو mw-content-text.
It looks like that div is inside of a chain of a few more divs.
يبدو أن عنصر div داخل سلسلة من بعض عناصر div الأخرى.
Excellent, if every article is structured like this one,
عمل رائع، إذا تم تنظيم كل مقال بهذه الطريقة،
then we should be able to use this information to do our web crawler.
يجب أن تمكن من استخدام هذه المعلومات لإنشاء متتبع الويب لدينا.